<resources>
    <string name="app_name">Mentawai TIC</string>
    <string name="museo_sans_rounded_100">fonts/MuseoSansRounded-100.otf</string>
    <string name="museo_sans_rounded_300">fonts/MuseoSansRounded-300.otf</string>
    <string name="museo_sans_rounded_500">fonts/MuseoSansRounded-500.otf</string>
    <string name="museo_sans_rounded_700">fonts/MuseoSansRounded-700.otf</string>

    <string name="aileuita">Aileuita</string>
    <string name="welcome">Welcome</string>
    <string name="how_are_you">"how are you"</string>
    <string name="loading">loading your profile</string>
    <string name="splash_title">The Government of Mentawai Island Regency\nThe West Sumatera Province</string>
    <string name="mentawai_surf_and_tourism">Mentawai Surf And Tourism</string>
    <string name="mentawai_surf_and_tourism_1">Mentawai\nSurf And\nTourism</string>
    <string name="mentawai_islands">Mentawai Islands</string>

    <string name="local_wisdom">Local Wisdom</string>
    <string name="local_wisdom_details">Local Wisdom of Arat Sabulungan</string>
    <string name="world_oldest_tattoo">World Oldest Tattoo</string>
    <string name="world_oldest_tattoo_details">The World Oldest Tattoo</string>
    <string name="attractions">Attractions</string>
    <string name="attractions_details">The Cultural Attractions Of Mentawai</string>
    <string name="nature">Nature</string>
    <string name="nature_details">Nature Mentawai</string>

    <string name="surfing_retribution">Surfing Retribution</string>
    <string name="surfing_spot">Surfing Spot</string>
    <string name="tides">Tides</string>
    <string name="tourism_information_center">Tourism Information Center</string>
    <string name="living_on_board">Living On Board</string>

    <string name="resorts">Resorts</string>
    <string name="homestay">Homestay</string>
    <string name="tour_guide">Tour Guide</string>
    <string name="island_life">Island Life</string>
    <string name="how_to_mentawai">How To Mentawai</string>

    <string name="mentawai_island_content" formatted="false">Before explore this “piece of paradise”, it is worth
    noted that it is part of West Sumatera Province covers 6.011,35 km2 wide with coast line
    stretched 1.402,66 km2 long. Geographically, Mentawai islands is separated from West Sumatera Province, bordered with Siberut
    strait on the South, Indian Ocean on the North, Mentawai strait on the East, and Indian Ocean on the West.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
    Before being mesmerized by the beauty of curling waves of Mentawai, which is dreamt by surfers from around the world, and cradling in
    the adventurous inland of Siberut, let us have a look to the profile of Mentawai to have a good
    understanding about the destinations.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
    Mentawai mainland covers 85 % forest. Within that percentage, 70 % is idle land and 25 % are rice fields, moor, mixed farms and plantations.
    Meanwhile the residential or housing area is only 3,042 hectares wide or 0.51 percent of the
    total area.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
    Mentawai regency has Tuapeijat as the capital, located in North Sipora district with 153km2 distance to Padang. Sea route and transport is
    the main access to reach the island from Padang, so as with local inter island transport especially between districts in Mentawai. The population
    of Mentawai Islands based on 2011 statistic was 77,078 people consisting of 40,632 male and 36,446 female.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
    From the illustration, we could now imagine that this regency stretch in a coastal areas with 95
    small uninhabited islands that scattered through four main islands of Siberut, Sipora, North and South Pagai Island.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
    Other useful information is that it is easier to access the coastal area in shore than travel deep
    onto the inland. This is because the infrastructure such as road and land transport is still very
    limited. For the entire district, the total length of the road is 465 miles.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
    According to the data, there are 13 seaports built around the four main islands. From the total 13 ports, eight of them are concrete construction, one iron construction, two constructed from
    timber, and two others are mix but for fish auction. The district distribution are as followed: three ports in Sikakap District, three ports in the District of North and South Sipora, three ports in the District of South Siberut, and one port in theDistrict of North Siberut.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
    Through these sea transport facilities, tourists can explore the beauty of the sea sights in the four main islands of Mentawai. If the weather
    and wave conditions are favorable, tourists can commute comfortably in and around Mentawai islands. Tourist can also make a stop over or visit
    some spots along the beaches. If the weather is good, chartered boats can anchored and parked at any location conveniently.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
    The Local Government of Mentawai District recorded 65 different kinds of tourist attractions in the area, which spread over in ten districts.
    From 65 tourist attractions, 21 of the attractions are natural scenery or scenic landscapes, 29
    </string>

    <string name="local_wisdom_content" formatted="false">The Mentawai Islands regency offers many
    charming natural tourism attractions. Perfect
    waves for surfing, beautiful underwater park, and
    white sandy beaches are few examples of them.
    The complement of this combination named
    “one of God’s masterpiece on earth”.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
    Unlike most tourist destinations, which have
    been touched by modernity, Mentawai Islands
    keep the humbleness in traditional identity. In
    some parts of the area, the authentic traditional
    way of life is remained protected by the local
    tribe due to their belief of “destroying forest
    means destroying life”.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
    The essential belief of indigenous Mentawaians
    says every living thing has its own spirit. They
    believe that forest is a dwelling place of the
    ancestors’ spirits who protect all plants and
    animals. Therefore, they have to treat the
    nature wisely and respectfully. The belief to the
    ancestors’ spirit and the wisdom to the nature
    for indigenous Mentawaians is called Arat
    Sabulungan.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;The evidence that indigenous Mentawaians
    respect the forest can be seen from the
    presence of leaves as the primary element in
    every Mentawaian traditional ceremony. The
    leaves are believed having healing powers. They
    even believe that the leaves are able to connect
    people with the Ruler of the universe. They called
    this belief as Ulau Manua.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
    Before cutting down a tree, the indigenous
    traditional Mentawaians do a ritual called Punen
    or Lia. This ritual is about asking permission
    to “the Spirit of the forest”. They also have to
    replace the felled off tree with a new one. This
    local wisdom is inherited and passed down
    from generation to generation. They believed
    that trees give life to human. This local wisdom
    attached tightly in the heart of Mentawai
    indigenous people.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
    As the result, humans and nature live
    harmoniously in hinterland of Mentawai. The
    sustainability of forest protection will ensure the
    preservation of the ecosystem. As the evidence,
    endemic wildlife and flora still can be found in
    the Mentawai Islands.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
    </string>

    <string name="world_oldest_content" formatted="false">Adi Rosa, a professor of Fine Arts from State
    University of Padang - West Sumatera, argued
    that Mentawai tribe has been tattooing their
    body since their arrival to the west coast of
    Sumatera in 1500 BC - 500 BC ago. It means
    Mentawai tattoo is one of the oldest tattoo in
    the world.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
    The tattoo is made by a Sipatiti (tattooist). The
    preparation of tattooing takes quite a long time,
    which can be up to several months. There are
    various ceremonies and taboos that must be
    passed by a person who wants to be tattooed.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
    Not everybody is able to pass through this stage.
    Needles that are used to tattoo are made from
    animal bone or sharpened Karai wood. The
    needle then wrought on the skin to create lines
    that become the main motif of Mentawai tribe
    tattoo. The dye is derived from charcoal that
    sticks in the cauldron. Usually, the process of
    tattooing starts from the palms, hands, feet, and
    body. After tattooing for several days, the skin
    that tattooed will swell and bleed.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
    Tattoo for Mentawai tribe is a symbol. Therefore,
    each streak and line has philosophical meaning.
    Besides describing the balance of the universe, it
    also contains the values of local wisdom that is
    inherited through generations.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
    According to Mentawai tribe, the main function
    of tattoo is to show identity and social status
    or profession. The tattoos of Sikerei (shaman)
    is different with tattoo of a hunter. The tattoo
    of a hunter will be identified from their sketch
    of hunted animals, such as pigs, deer, monkeys,
    birds, or crocodiles. The Sikerei’s tattoos can
    be identified by “stars motif tattoo” known as
    Sibalu- balu.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
    In short, tattoo for the indigenous people of
    Mentawai is a purification stage of body and soul
    in order to achieve perfect harmony with the
    spirit of the universe.</string>

    <string name="attractions_content" formatted="false">There are 14 types of dances that commonly
    held in traditional ceremonies which are; clap
    dance, boating dance, eagle dance, chicken
    dance, monkey dance, healing dance, butterfly
    dance, fields dance, sparrow dance, owl dance,
    snatching lover dance, prodigal son dance, and
    gull dance. There are leaves ornament in almost
    all of the traditional clothes used by the dancers.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
    Additionally, visitors can also witness the sacred
    and magical rituals of Mentawai indigenous
    people in Siberut. This ritual is performed
    at certain time depends on its purpose; for
    example, the ritual treatment of the sick and the
    ritual of casting out the demons.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
    In the North Pagai, for example, visitors can enjoy
    the interesting sights when the women and
    the girls fishing in the shallow estuaries. Women
    usually go to the river looking for the seashell
    and shrimp using ‘Subba ‘, this activity called
    Manairi.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
    Not only in the river, the swamp around the
    mangrove forest is also a source of food for the
    indigenous people such as seashell or scallop.
    They looking for the seashell or scallop in the
    mud mangrove forests by immersed their hands
    on mud.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
    There is also Anggau tradition, crabs searching
    by the people of Mentawai. However, the
    Anggau tradition is not a routine activity, but
    only in certain seasons mainly in the wavy
    season.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
    There is also Otcai tradition. Otcai is a tradition of
    distributing food equally to each tribal chief in
    every Uma. Otcai means togetherness. Dividing
    the otcai is held in wedding ceremonies or other
    rituals.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
    Another tradition which unfortunately almost
    extinct in Mentawai is Pakilia. Pakilia is a
    welcoming ceremony of the new member of the
    family or tribe. Usually, Pakilia performed after the
    wedding ceremony.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
    An interesting ceremony that visitors can
    witness in Siberut is Panunggru ceremony. It
    is a ritual that ending the mourning period of
    a dead person in a family. This ritual embraces
    the philosophy of parting forever between the
    spirits of the deceased to the bereaved family.
    Therefore, the ceremony is held few months after
    the burial.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
    The Mentawaians also play a traditional musical
    instrument called Taddukat. The instrument is
    played when one of the member of the tribe die.</string>

    <string name="nature_content" formatted="false">There are at least four natural attractions worth
    to visit during travelling to Mentawai. First is the
    waterfall. There are some waterfalls located in the
    island of North Siberut. One of the most famous
    is Sirilanngai waterfall in Malancan village,
    which has pristine and natural condition. Other
    waterfalls are in Simantamtaman Monganpoula,
    Sirilanggai Cimpungan, and Kulukubuk
    The second natural attraction is lake. There is
    a beautiful lake can be found in the middle
    of the forest in Saumanganyak village, known
    as Rua Oinan Lake. This estuary shape lake is
    surrounded by big trees. The other lakes are
    located in Gojib Simalegi (Siberut) and Rua
    Oinan Saumanganyak (North Pagai).&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
    The third tourism attraction is adventure through
    the river. Mentawai has many rivers because it
    mainly covered by forest, which has river flowing
    inside it. Since the forests are well protected and
    the water is still clean; therefore it is really ideal
    for travelers who want to go trekking and hiking
    around the area. Some numbers of spots that
    can be visited are, Sagulubbeg, Taileleu, Muara
    Sikabaluan, and Policoman.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
    Mentawai also offers the excitement of seeing
    exotic wildlife. Visitor can explore the beauty of
    Mentawai endemic flora and fauna. Based on the
    local official record of Mentawai district, there
    are four types of endemic primates, namely Bilou
    (gibbon species), Joja (ape species), Simakobu
    (pig-tailed macaque species), Bokkoi (monkey
    species), 17 species of mammals, 150 types
    of birds, one of which is Mentawai owl (Otus
    Mentawai) and 98 species of orchids.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
    There is an interesting belief about Bilou, the
    primate. For the indigenous people of Mentawai,
    Bilou’s voice is considered as a sign. When
    Bilou sounds a heartbreaking groan, it means
    something bad is going to happen, death for
    example. When they make noisy sounds, people
    believe that will be an earthquake coming.
    The Mentawai islands are covered with the
    tropical rainforest includes dipterocarp forest,
    a mixture of primary forests, swamps, coastal
    forests to mangroves area. Each island has
    their own flora, which is estimated that 15% of
    existing plants are endemic.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
    About 65% of the mammals in Mentawai are
    endemic animals (only exist in the islands). All of
    them can be found at the Conservation Areas of
    Siberut Sagulubbeg, Taileleu, Muara Sikabaluan,
    Policoman Policoman Forest (North Siberu)</string>

    <string name="surfing_retribution_content" formatted="false">In the period 80-90’s, foreign surfers “dominated”
    the big waves and enjoyed the barrel freely in the waters around the Mentawai Islands. From
    their adventures of hunting waves, one by one, the foreign surfers gave names on “waves” they found.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
    According to the surfers, surfing in Mentawai is more challenging and fun, because of the wave
    and beach character are more vary. They named various types of waves, such as mellow, hollow,
    and barrel, so that the surfer can enjoy different type of waves they can surf.</string>

    <string name="surfing_spot_content" formatted="false">Another advantage surfing in Mentawais is the friendly distance between the waves. The waves
    have an adequate interval: Not too short or too long. Waves in Mentawai have sufficient intervals, preventing surfers pushed by two or more
    consecutive large waves. The situation is often called a triple hold-down. Injure or death does
    happen in surfing because some surfers cannot anticipate such triple hold-down in the crowded location.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
    Well, the wave’s interval, types, height, cleanliness or smoothness, and the number of surf spots or surfers in one spot, are the factors that should be
    taken into account to assess whether a surf spot was good, not good, or bad.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
    In this regard, surfing spots in the Mentawai is scored 9, which is consider perfect among the surfers. These are conditions that make
    Mentawai is favorable than other surfing areas in the world.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
    Pulau Roniki Kec. Siberut Barat Daya&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
    • Burgerworld Right&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
    • Burgerworld Left&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
    • E-bay Left&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
    </string>

    <string name="how_to_mentawai_content" formatted="false">
    There are two modes of transport to reach Mentawai, by plane and boat. Whatever the choice, both would create memorable experience to the visitors. If visitors choose
    for the sea transportation, they can go from the Port of Bungus, West Sumatra. ASDP (River, Lake and Crossing Transport) ships will take visitors to the Mentawai Islands. There
    are two ships that have a fixed schedule: KM Ambu Ambu and KM Gambolo, which can take people to the four main islands in Mentawai. It will took approximately 8 (eight)
    to 12 (twelve) hours transport, leaving the port around 17:00 or 20:00, and arriving at the destination when the sky is red tinge in the eastern horizon. &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
    Besides ASDP ships, there are also fast boat which operate by private company with limited capacity that can be chartered. The boat departs from the port of Muara, Padang.
    Unfortunately, chartered boat is quite costly. Currently, there is a fast ship called Mentawai Fast, which is ready to take tourists to explore the islands in the Mentawai islands in a short hours and the cost is affordable. &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
    Visitors can also access Mentawai by plane. From Minangkabau International Airport in Padang, there are direct flights to the airport of Rokot, at the Sipora Island. The Aircraft
    named Susi Airline have three times flights schedule in a week to go to Rokot Airport.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
    When visiting Mentawai, visitors do not need to worry about accommodation. In the four main islands and small islands around it, there are many resorts, hotels, guesthouses
    and other accommodation facilities scattered throughout the island. The price is varied, ranging from low up to high budget. Even when tourists want to visit the inland of
    Siberut, there are many houses that can be used as a homestay.
    </string>

    <string name="resorts_content" formatted="false">
    1. KANDUI RESORT&lt;br /&gt;
    Pulau Karamajat, Desa Katurei&lt;br /&gt;
    www.kanduiresort.com&lt;br /&gt;

    &lt;br /&gt;

    2. KANDUI VILLAS RESORT&lt;br /&gt;
    Pulau Karamajat, Desa Katurei&lt;br /&gt;
	www.kanduivillas.com&lt;br /&gt;

    &lt;br /&gt;

    3. WAVEPARK RESORT&lt;br /&gt;
    Pulau mainuk, Desa Katurei&lt;br /&gt;
	www.wavepark.com&lt;br /&gt;

    &lt;br /&gt;

    4. PITT STOP HILL&lt;br /&gt;
    Pulau Nyang Nyang, Desa Taileleu&lt;br /&gt;
	www.pitstophill.com&lt;br /&gt;
    </string>

    <string name="homestay_content" formatted="false">
    &lt;b&gt;Sikakap&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
    Wisma Bagindo&lt;br /&gt;
    Wisma Lestari&lt;br /&gt;
    Wisma Kita 082170227873&lt;br /&gt;
    Wisma Asri&lt;br /&gt;
    Wisma Berkah 0759- 322233

    &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;

    &lt;b&gt;Sipora Utara&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
    Lalep Oinan Guest House&lt;br /&gt;
    081363405801 (Johanes)&lt;br /&gt;
    Km. 4 Mapadegat,desa Tuapeijat&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
    Baruni Homestay&lt;br /&gt;
    Mapadegat, desa Tuapeijat&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
    Hotel Turonia&lt;br /&gt;
	0759-320578,320579&lt;br /&gt;
	081267405321&lt;br /&gt;
    Km. 5, desa Tuapeijat&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
    Bundo Guest House&lt;br /&gt;
	081374577708&lt;br /&gt;
    Km. 6, desa Tuapeijat&lt;br /&gt;
    </string>

</resources>
